Guide to the Michael McVaugh Papers, 1971-1988 and undated RL.11609
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Michael McVaugh papers
1971-1988 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McVaugh, M.R. (Michael Rogers), 1938-
RL.11609
1.0 Linear Feet
Michael McVaugh is professor emeritus of history at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Collection comprises his research, interviews, and preparation for the book, The Elusive Science, coauthored with Seymour Mauskopf, regarding the research of J. B. Rhine and the Parapsychology Laboratory at Duke University. Interview and research subjects include Hans Bender, Knight Dunlap, Hudson Hoagland, John L. Kennedy, Brian Mackenzie, Gardner Murphy, Harry Price, Gertrude Schmeidler, Ernest Taves, Raymond Willoughby, Dael Wolfle, and George Zirkle.
Biographical / Historical
Michael McVaugh is professor emeritus of history at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. He received his bachelor's degree from Harvard and his Ph.D. from Princeton, and came to Chapel Hill, North Carolina, in 1964 to teach the history of science in the history department of the University of North Carolina. During the late 1960s he began a close collaborative relationship with Seymour Mauskopf at Duke University, fusing the two programs in the history of science. The two collaborated in a study of the history of parapsychology under J. B. Rhine at Duke, The Elusive Science: Origins of Experimental Psychical Research (Johns Hopkins, 1980), which was one of the early monographs to recognize the importance of treating the history of science as more than simply a record of transcendent intellectual accomplishments. But the bulk of Professor McVaugh's research has centered on medicine in the medieval and early modern periods. In 1996 Professor McVaugh was named William Smith Wells Professor of History at the University of North Carolina; he retired from formal teaching in 2007. He was made a Fellow of the Medieval Academy of America in 2005 and received the Sarton Medal of the History of Science Society in 2010.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Michael McVaugh Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018.
Related Materials
See the Seymour Mauskopf Papers and the Parapsychology Laboratory Records in the Rubenstein Library holdings.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises his research, interviews, and preparation for the book, The Elusive Science, coauthored with Seymour Mauskopf, regarding the research of J. B. Rhine and the Parapsychology Laboratory at Duke University. Interview and research subjects include Hans Bender, Knight Dunlap, Hudson Hoagland, John L. Kennedy, Brian Mackenzie, Gardner Murphy, Harry Price, Gertrude Schmeidler, Ernest Taves, Raymond Willoughby, Dael Wolfle, and George Zirkle.
Conditions Governing Access
A Nitrate Negative is stored in box one and may not be used in the reading room. A use copy of the negative is available in the ESP Photos folder.
Parapsychology -- Research -- History; Bender, Hans, 1907-1991; Dunlap, Knight, 1875-1949; Hoagland, Hudson, 1899-1982; Mauskopf, Seymour H. -- Elusive Science; Murphy, Gardner, 1895-1979; Price, Harry, 1881-1948; Rhine, J. B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Schmeidler, Gertrude Raffel; Willoughby, Raymond Royce; Wolfle, Dael, 1906-2002; Duke University. Psychology Department; Mauskopf, Seymour H.
- Rhine comments, Chapters 4 & 9, undated (Box 1)
- For the Rhines, Chapter 5, 6/18/79 (Box 1)
- Chapter 6, undated (Box 1)
- Chapters 6 & 7 revised, Sy Mauskopf, 7/17/79 (Box 1)
- Chapter 8, undated (Box 1)
- Chapter 9, undated (Box 1)
- Chapter 10, undated (Box 1)
- Contacts, 1972-1988 and undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, copyeditor, 1979-1981 and undated (Box 1)
- ESP photos, 1979-1980 and undated (Box 1)
- NITRATE NEGATIVE (Box 1)
- Interviews, prospectus, 1971-1977 and undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Mauskopf, 1971-1982 and undated (Box 2)
- Bender, 1977-1979 and undated (Box 2)
- Dunlap--proposals for ESP technique, undated (Box 2)
- Heymans, undated (Box 2)
- Hoagland, 1975 and undated (Box 2)
- Kennedy, 1976 and undated (Box 2)
- MacKenzie, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 2)
- Gardner Murphy, undated (Box 2)
- Harry Price, 1977 and undated (Box 2)
- Schmeidler, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 3)
- Taves, 1979 and undated (Box 3)
- Willoughby, undated (Box 3)
- Wolfle, 1974-1979 and undated (Box 3)
- Zirkle, undated (Box 3)
- A program for research on the hypothesis of survival, 1945 (Box 3)